<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

    <title>crodjer's blogRoll</title>
    <link href="http://www.rohanjain.in/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
    <link href="http://www.rohanjain.in/"/>
    <updated>2012-03-26T11:45:59+05:30</updated>
    <id>http://www.rohanjain.in/</id>
    <author>
        <name>Rohan Jain</name>
        <email>crodjer@gmail.com</email>
    </author>

    
    <entry>
        <title>An experience with PHP</title>
        <link href="http://www.rohanjain.in/hacking/2012/01/30/an-experience-with-php"/>
        <updated>2012-01-30T00:00:00+05:30</updated>
        <id>http://www.rohanjain.in/hacking/2012/01/30/an-experience-with-php</id>
        
        <category term="hacking" />
        
        <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I have always tried to stay away from PHP. Python has always been my language
of choice. But, recently I got to write a considerable amount of code in PHP,
for my current projects. They are based on a web framework called
&lt;a href=&quot;http://codeigniter.com/&quot;&gt;Codeigniter&lt;/a&gt;. Being completely inexperienced in
writing production code with PHP, I did struggle with it a bit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a language PHP has its pros and cons. This post includes my personal
opinions so, tagged as &amp;lsquo;subjective&amp;rsquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;pros&quot;&gt;Pros&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;comprehensive-documentation&quot;&gt;Comprehensive documentation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;PHP has a really high adoption, so has a rather comprehensive amount of
resources available over the web. If you run into some issue, you can mostly be
sure that some else has had the same issue as well proceed as that person did.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;c-like-syntax&quot;&gt;C like syntax&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The syntax is not much alien to C, which is a language most of the programmers
know from their &amp;ldquo;Programming 101&amp;rdquo;s. So the initial slope of the learning curve
is not steep.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;lots-of-libraries&quot;&gt;Lots of libraries&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Want to implement something? There is probably an existing library which does
that for me. Hence, you can save yourself from writing lots of code. Infact for
any new web technology PHP is always amongst the languages which get a
library first.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;common-web-development-language&quot;&gt;Common web development language&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If one is assembling a team, it is probably true that PHP developers will be
the easiest to find. So one could just choose PHP as the language.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;closures&quot;&gt;Closures&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With PHP 5.3 and up, anonymous functions are available. These are very useful,
particularly in array maps and callbacks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;cons&quot;&gt;Cons&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the--operator&quot;&gt;The &lt;code&gt;||&lt;/code&gt; operator&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The results from the or (&lt;code&gt;||&lt;/code&gt;) should be one of the operands instead it returns
&lt;code&gt;1&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;0&lt;/code&gt; which is useless most of the time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;error-reporting&quot;&gt;Error reporting&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lot of errors that occur while execution, just fail silently or with warnings
and the execution continues. Why not just halt the script execution and let
the programmers deal with it, they can take it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;there-are-no-promises&quot;&gt;There are no promises&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You cannot promise PHP that &lt;code&gt;foo&lt;/code&gt; will return an array, so it is not possible
to just do &lt;code&gt;foo(arg)['key']&lt;/code&gt; to get a particular index of the array resulting
from the function call.  Instead a temporary variable, &lt;code&gt;$foo_result&lt;/code&gt; is needed.
Because of this you can&amp;rsquo;t chain function calls to apply multiple functions
over a variable. This is particularly annoying with arrays, while doing various
manipulations over them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;embedding-code-in-html&quot;&gt;Embedding code in HTML&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some might say that this is a good thing, but I don&amp;rsquo;t believe so. This doesn&amp;rsquo;t
let you decouple the templates from the application back end. Templates get
too much power and projects end up with some application logic in templates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;lots-of-libraries-1&quot;&gt;Lots of libraries&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wasn&amp;rsquo;t this a pro too? It was but this also has some negative effect. There
are multiple libraries available, sometimes for doing the same task. They
don&amp;rsquo;t have wide contexts. Each might fulfill functionality that one requires
partially but not all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;PHP is definitely a major server side scripting language. Its popularity, the
ease to build developer teams counts as a reason for choosing PHP. But, given
a choice, PHP will always be on the lower side of my priority list. I&amp;rsquo;ll
mostly go with full fledged languages like Python. With
&lt;a href=&quot;http://couchdb.apache.org/&quot;&gt;CouchDB&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://nodejs.org/&quot;&gt;node.js&lt;/a&gt;
around, server side Javascript also looks promising. To get around their
limitations they can always be used in parallel with other systems.
Its better to have multiple decoupled systems, providing reasonable APIs and
implemented in a technology best for each of them, talk to each other instead
of writing everything down in the same language.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </entry>
    
    <entry>
        <title>Awesome is here</title>
        <link href="http://www.rohanjain.in/personal/2011/09/08/finally-got-my-comp"/>
        <updated>2011-09-08T00:00:00+05:30</updated>
        <id>http://www.rohanjain.in/personal/2011/09/08/finally-got-my-comp</id>
        
        <category term="personal" />
        
        <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Some time ago, I &lt;a href=&quot;/personal/2011/08/11/what-i-learnt-about-buying-computers/&quot;&gt;wrote about my search&lt;/a&gt;
for a notebook, which does exactly what I need it to. It is an &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.flipkart.com/computers/laptops/hp/itmczxzyhgkabvgp&quot;&gt;HP 630
Essential Business PC&lt;/a&gt;.
The price is very much reasonable for the hardware it has and the useless stuff
(some windows pre-installations, replaceable lid covers, graphic card etc.) it
does not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Actually, I had bought it some time ago but didn&amp;rsquo;t write about it earlier as I
was waiting for its configuration to be complete so that it can be titled
&lt;strong&gt;awesome&lt;/strong&gt; (as was my old one). Now that it has a 6 Gigs of RAM and a fast OCz
&lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Solid-state_drive&quot;&gt;SSD&lt;/a&gt; my hardware upgrade is
finally complete so that I could brag about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.debian.org/releases/sid/&quot;&gt;debian sid&lt;/a&gt; installation with &lt;a href=&quot;http://awesome.naquadah.org/&quot;&gt;awesome
wm&lt;/a&gt; (not directly related to the machine&amp;rsquo;s title)
and linux 3.0 is working pretty nicely. I have made sure that each and every
hardware works. The processor turbo boosts up to 2.9 GHz when GCC asks to,
graphics are pretty good and nothing makes any sound at all (the SSD adds to
the fact). To my surprise the touchpad turned out to be really great. Although
I had already given up the mouse, the pad makes sure that whenever the tragic
need of moving the mouse cursor comes (sometimes with chrome) it&amp;rsquo;ll ease it up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another interesting fact about my configuration is the Standing Table (yeah I
don&amp;rsquo;t sit while working). This is how the whole setup looks like:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://i1105.photobucket.com/albums/h356/crodjer/Blog%20Posts/Standing%20Table/Image0123.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Standing Table&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;http://i1105.photobucket.com/albums/h356/crodjer/Blog%20Posts/Standing%20Table/Image0124.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Standing Table Under Focus&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;update&quot;&gt;Update&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have switched back to a left right configuration again. The experience of
stating table was nice, but wasn&amp;rsquo;t sustainable for I was experiencing issues
of space management.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </entry>
    
    <entry>
        <title>Configure ssh to handle proxies and tunnels seamlessly</title>
        <link href="http://www.rohanjain.in/hacking/2011/08/27/configure-ssh-to-handle-proxies-and-tunnels-seamlessly"/>
        <updated>2011-08-27T00:00:00+05:30</updated>
        <id>http://www.rohanjain.in/hacking/2011/08/27/configure-ssh-to-handle-proxies-and-tunnels-seamlessly</id>
        
        <category term="hacking" />
        
        <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Recently I opened up on the port &lt;em&gt;443&lt;/em&gt; over my EC2 instance (more or less like
a VPS), so that I can access it through any firewalled proxy too. Apart from
getting SSH running to a machine from outside world, I did some cool
configuration to have ssh deal with with various remote hosts automatically. It
uses &lt;em&gt;the right&lt;/em&gt; proxy settings according the host being accessed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All the stuff which runs over ssh (like &lt;em&gt;scp&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;git&lt;/em&gt; etc.) also work the way
they are supposed to, following the ssh configuration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To get this to work you need to have &lt;em&gt;corkscrew&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;netcat&lt;/em&gt; (the swiss army
knife) already installed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is how it goes:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;code&gt;File ~/ssh/config:&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Update&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
As brought out by yeban (&lt;a href=&quot;http://yeban.in/seamlessly-use-github-behind-http-proxy-on-port-443.html&quot;&gt;http://yeban.in/seamlessly-use-github-behind-http-proxy-on-port-443.html&lt;/a&gt;),
use github&amp;rsquo;s 443 ssh host for accessing github.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </entry>
    
    <entry>
        <title>My new music solution</title>
        <link href="http://www.rohanjain.in/hacking/2011/08/24/my-new-music-solution"/>
        <updated>2011-08-24T00:00:00+05:30</updated>
        <id>http://www.rohanjain.in/hacking/2011/08/24/my-new-music-solution</id>
        
        <category term="hacking" />
        
        <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;As far as listening to music is concerned, I have always been relying on the
various radio broadcasters. I do not invest much time in maintaining a music
collection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But this solution did not work at Kharagpur. There is no good radio station
available over here, at least for listening to Hindi music. I then turned
to the various online radio services, which seemed to work out pretty nice.
Now all I needed a good interface to control the radio. The Rhythmbox interface
and that of some other radio clients from the Debian repository did not look
friendly (chuck the mouse and then test them). Here comes the mplayer to the
rescue, which I am using currently.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also created this shell script which stores the channels as key value pairs
and invokes mplayer with correct proxy settings.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
    </entry>
    
    <entry>
        <title>What I learnt about buying computers</title>
        <link href="http://www.rohanjain.in/personal/2011/08/11/what-i-learnt-about-buying-computers"/>
        <updated>2011-08-11T00:00:00+05:30</updated>
        <id>http://www.rohanjain.in/personal/2011/08/11/what-i-learnt-about-buying-computers</id>
        
        <category term="personal" />
        
        <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Some months ago I decided about the what my new &lt;a href=&quot;http://j.mp/o043VH&quot;&gt;computer&amp;rsquo;s configuration&lt;/a&gt;
will be. It was a really powerful machine with all the latest
parts (they still are latest!). Its main strength was the new intel processor
architecture - &lt;a href=&quot;http://j.mp/qbjSyR&quot;&gt;Sandy Bridge&lt;/a&gt;. I had ruled out laptops
considering the higer costs with lower configuration and absence of the Sandy
Bridge architecture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But due to unavailablility of processor and motherboard in India, I had to wait
for a long time till I figured out how to get all the parts. While the wait, I
started doing a smart upgrade of my existing notebook. I got a new monitor,
keyboard (The generic stuff). The one unique thing that not many people try was
a &lt;strong&gt;Solid State Drive&lt;/strong&gt; (glad I am enjoying one). About this time only I took
a look at the detailed configuration of my laptop and upgrade options. I was
surprised to see that the maximum resolution the machine served was upto
8192 x 8192. After the SSD and a memory upgrade I was surprised to see the
performance boost and thanks it was giving me back. I was having all the fun
using multiple screens and not caring if I left any programs open. So I decided
to not get any new machine at all and keep using my CQ40-144TU for a while till
I find something worth upgrading in the market.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since the time when I first decided for a new machine and now, I saw that there
were a &lt;em&gt;lot&lt;/em&gt; of notebooks availabe with the &lt;em&gt;2nd Generation Core i series&lt;/em&gt;
(Sandy Bridge) processors and at compelling prices. So I started a new search
with queries: &lt;strong&gt;Intel HD Graphics 3000&lt;/strong&gt; (Ensures Sandy Bridge arch. and no
power hungry graphics card), &lt;strong&gt;Core i5&lt;/strong&gt; (Ensures hyper threading and more than
required processing power) and &lt;strong&gt;Free DOS&lt;/strong&gt; (Of Course! - I dont want to waste
such a nice notebook with windows). There are some notebooks which come out
as reasonable buys.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I ruled out Dell on the first go as it only seems like it that they allow you
to customize, but they don&amp;rsquo;t. If you want a simple machine without &lt;a href=&quot;http://j.mp/o7Zb36&quot;&gt;all the
useless&lt;/a&gt; (it is subjective) stuffs like Online backup (If I
wanted one I would use a VPS , Windows (I can&amp;rsquo;t understand why force it!) or
replaceable covers (I am getting a computer not a doll to play with!). What I
want is a processor + motherboard with some notebook essentials with it. HP and
ThinkPads are the brands I am looking at now. They provide some business
notebooks which serve all my purposes.&lt;br /&gt;
I&amp;rsquo;ll tell about the final machine which I bought in some newer post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Still, I would always miss my old machine, which has always been there with me
for roughly 1.5 years. It is still doing pretty good (This post is written with
one only) and has more upgrade capabilities. It is well over &lt;em&gt;good enough&lt;/em&gt; as a
general usage computer.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </entry>
    
    <entry>
        <title>An incident on the RAILS</title>
        <link href="http://www.rohanjain.in/personal/2011/07/18/an-incident-on-the-rails"/>
        <updated>2011-07-18T00:00:00+05:30</updated>
        <id>http://www.rohanjain.in/personal/2011/07/18/an-incident-on-the-rails</id>
        
        <category term="personal" />
        
        <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;After having marvellous summers, I was comming back to collage. It is a tiring
jounrney of total 30 hrs. First Jaipur-Howrah and then to Kharagpur from there.
I was happy as I had got my confirmed reservation: Seat 32 in B-1 (It is nearly
impossible to get a confirmed reservation in that train). The boarding time was
2 AM in the morning (or night?).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I boarded the train and headed to my seat, only to find out it was already
occupied. &lt;em&gt;Mr. A&lt;/em&gt; was sitting there. So we (my parents had comewith me to see me
of) asked Mr. A to move as this seat was reserved on my name (I had checked out
my name on the reservation chart already). He says &amp;ldquo;This is not my seat, I have
exchanged it with him (pointing to &lt;em&gt;Mr. B&lt;/em&gt;)&amp;rdquo;. So on asking the same to Mr. B,
he also replied the same pointing to &lt;em&gt;Mr. X&lt;/em&gt;  and finally, we found the
conflicting passanger. 5 - 6 people of the cabin had woken up from their sleeps
because of all the noise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr. X had a ticket which said &amp;ldquo;B-1 32&amp;rdquo; over the same train number and the right
date of the month. Believe me about 4 -5 people checked the ticked, including
myself. Infact it had a signature of a TC denoting &lt;em&gt;verified&lt;/em&gt;. This guy was
adament and refusing to talk. We contacted the current TC who also agreed that
it was my seat. He asked me to at least get the conflicting ticket as Mr. X
wasn&amp;rsquo;t comming down. Finally he also decided to accompany me with his ticket
mouthing bad words to the official. The ticket looked all OK to him too, before
his eyes went on the month. It was a ticket of the train&amp;rsquo;s next month journy!
The guy then silently unboarded with his stuff and maybe boarded a general
compartment. Everybody who had exchanged &amp;ldquo;his&amp;rdquo; seat came back to theirs. Almost
everybody from the cabin was awake now. And I got my seat on the train.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe Mr. X didn&amp;rsquo;t know that he was travelling in the wrong month or he had
booked a wrong ticket (more probable) or he was thinking that he could fool
the system (I dont feel sorry for him at all if this were the truth).&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </entry>
    
    <entry>
        <title>Django using admin horizontal filter in forms</title>
        <link href="http://www.rohanjain.in/hacking/2011/06/20/django-using-admin-horizontal-filter-in-forms"/>
        <updated>2011-06-20T00:00:00+05:30</updated>
        <id>http://www.rohanjain.in/hacking/2011/06/20/django-using-admin-horizontal-filter-in-forms</id>
        
        <category term="hacking" />
        
        <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The django admin filter horizontal/vertical widgets are a really cool
replacement of the inconvenient and ugly default multiple select elements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://i1105.photobucket.com/albums/h356/crodjer/Blog%20Posts/Selection_010.png&quot; alt=&quot;Django admin filter used in auth&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;But how do I get these in my normal forms?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
This is how:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First create a django form with &lt;code&gt;ModelMultipleChoiceField&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;FilterSelectMultiple&lt;/code&gt;
as widget. To get this to work you need to add some extra media files. Here
is the snipet:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;forms.py&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Add form media and form in the template.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This extra css fixes some layout problems&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Refrences: &lt;a href=&quot;http://j.mp/mAzALa&quot;&gt;http://j.mp/mAzALa&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://j.mp/lIG2Fl&quot;&gt;http://j.mp/lIG2Fl&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
I decided to create another post for this because, none of these suggests
the use of admin widget directly.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </entry>
    
    <entry>
        <title>Dynamic to Static</title>
        <link href="http://www.rohanjain.in/personal/2011/06/16/dynamic-to-static"/>
        <updated>2011-06-16T00:00:00+05:30</updated>
        <id>http://www.rohanjain.in/personal/2011/06/16/dynamic-to-static</id>
        
        <category term="personal" />
        
        <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I just shifted my website to Jekyll static pages, from the completely
dynamic &lt;em&gt;django&lt;/em&gt; based and database oriented &lt;a href=&quot;http://old.rohanjain.in&quot;&gt;old one&lt;/a&gt;.
The factor which drove this decision: &lt;strong&gt;VIM&lt;/strong&gt; period.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did not put up much on the old site because I couldn&amp;rsquo;t post directly from
my offline editor to posts there. The functionalities that were present over
there were to much overkill and completely invisible to the public, so better
save the processing power required to render the content every time the
page is accessed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the setting up of this, I expect a considerable increase in my
blogging frequency.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </entry>
    
    <entry>
        <title>Building my power computer</title>
        <link href="http://www.rohanjain.in/personal/2011/04/22/building-my-power-computer"/>
        <updated>2011-04-22T00:00:00+05:30</updated>
        <id>http://www.rohanjain.in/personal/2011/04/22/building-my-power-computer</id>
        
        <category term="personal" />
        
        <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I have been using laptops as working machines for 3 years now. With my ancient
C2D 2GHz, I can&amp;rsquo;t play games (I don&amp;rsquo;t anyways but still), use powerfull
applications and am able to &lt;strong&gt;blink my eyes&lt;/strong&gt; (much more than once sometimes)
for most of the executions. This asks for system upgrades. But wait! upgrade
and laptop seem to be mutually exclusive. Now this is bad. I think &lt;em&gt;What is
the reason to buy laptops?&lt;/em&gt;. I find only one: &lt;strong&gt;Portablity&lt;/strong&gt;. But is it really
worth spending &lt;strong&gt;lots&lt;/strong&gt; of extra bucks just to achieve portability, which too
come at price of way lower configuration? Aren&amp;rsquo;t tablets the one for portability?  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking for a good laptop around, I found to get one with i7 drains around
90k-100k Rs and still the configuration will be way low end against the one
I can get according to below one of a desktop. So I get a really powerfull
desktop and save up enough to get a good Tablet for portability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A rough configuration of the rig I finnaly decided:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Processor&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;a href=&quot;http://j.mp/kYM47y&quot;&gt;Core™ i7-2600K&lt;/a&gt; (Sandy Bridge)&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Rs. 17,000&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mother Board&lt;/strong&gt;: Z68 chipset based (&lt;a href=&quot;http://j.mp/k3kM8f&quot;&gt;ASUS&lt;/a&gt;/&lt;a href=&quot;http://j.mp/mnvdYo&quot;&gt;GIGABYTE&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Rs. 12,000 - 16,000&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Graphics&lt;/strong&gt;: None or &lt;a href=&quot;http://j.mp/iSqbvu&quot;&gt;GeForce GT 430&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Rs. 0 - 5,000&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;RAM&lt;/strong&gt;: 2X4GB DDR3&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Rs. 5,000 - 6,000&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hard Drive&lt;/strong&gt;
Mechanical 1-1.5 TB WD/Seagate : Rs. 3,600 - 5,500
SSD 64GB : Rs. 8, 000 - 9, 000
&lt;strong&gt;Rs. 12,000 - 14,000&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DVD RW&lt;/strong&gt;: Rs. 1,200&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Case + Power&lt;/strong&gt;: Rs. 5,000 - 7,500&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Monitor&lt;/strong&gt;: Rs. 7,500 - 10,000&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which total around &lt;strong&gt;Rs. 56,000 - 65,000&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whole analysis at my old website &lt;a href=&quot;http://j.mp/isxQGU&quot;&gt;http://j.mp/isxQGU&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </entry>
    
    <entry>
        <title>Hosting multiple sites with same django project</title>
        <link href="http://www.rohanjain.in/hacking/2010/12/24/hosting-multiple-sites-with-same-django-project"/>
        <updated>2010-12-24T00:00:00+05:30</updated>
        <id>http://www.rohanjain.in/hacking/2010/12/24/hosting-multiple-sites-with-same-django-project</id>
        
        <category term="hacking" />
        
        <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The first thing the title triggers in the mind is the django &lt;a href=&quot;http://docs.djangoproject.com/en/dev/ref/contrib/sites/&quot;&gt;sites framework&lt;/a&gt;. Well this post is mostly related to that but suggests its utilization in slight different way. As we can get from the docs in every implementation of the sites framework you have to hardcode the SITE_ID in your settings.py file. So it assumes that you have multiple django projects or at least multiple settings.py files which will be used as the django settings module for the process. So basically it provides us to share database between multiple sites which is a nice feature.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For our case which is, we want to use a single django project to across multiple domains while presenting altered versions of content dependant on the originating domain (the domain names cannot be hardcoded as the number of domains is dynamic too.), we have to do something different to get this level of dynamicity. I did sone research about this on the &lt;strong&gt;#django&lt;/strong&gt; IRC, &lt;strong&gt;stackoverflow&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;google&lt;/strong&gt;. Here are some complete/incomplete ways I found out to achieve this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;using-custom-apps-and-modules&quot;&gt;Using custom apps and modules&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These ways would need us to define many custom models and middleware, hence a lot of work. The domain management would be done by the django project itself through middleware which use the HTTP_REQUST header and hence every request will be processed to obtain the information required to do database queries and render the views. So these methods looks like bit safer but would cause a performance decrease. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;modify-contrib&quot;&gt;Modify contrib&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the rather easier way which involves modifications of code of some django contrib apps here and there. 
Just copy the apps from django-&amp;gt;contrib folder to the project directory and modify them to accept request as argument give out results according to the HTTP_HOST and Sites database. Also change all the imo reference of these apps from &lt;em&gt;django.contrib.app&lt;/em&gt; to &lt;em&gt;app&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;forget-contrib&quot;&gt;Forget contrib&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another way would be to forget the contrib apps and write your own custom similar ones from scratch. This may be a better way for long term projects which require highly customized and special functionalities. But it will require us to write a lot of code, though the existing modules can be used for reference. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;using-unaltered-django-modules&quot;&gt;Using unaltered django modules&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we are successful in doing this it will probably let us build our project in much less lines of code and using the already existent django contribs as is. So if we don&amp;rsquo;t modify django modules then what do we modify to achieve the dynamicity. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;wsgi&quot;&gt;.wsgi&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is what we could do: First define multiple settings files in some pattern so that they can be matched according to the domain name, say &lt;em&gt;settings_domain.py&lt;/em&gt;. Now if the deployment is done using wsgi script (generally in &lt;a href=&quot;http://docs.djangoproject.com/en/dev/howto/deployment/modwsgi/&quot;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt;) format. In the wsgi script we have to call the respective settings_domain.py according to the accessing domain name. So this seems pretty good but it can be dangerous. As we are setting a global variable (&lt;code&gt;os.environ['DJANGO_SETTINGS_MODULE']&lt;/code&gt;) it is not at all a &lt;strong&gt;thread safe&lt;/strong&gt; method. If there are two requests close enough this may pose dangerous effects. Unless we are not able to make sure that a new fork / new wsgi demon will be created per domain. So maybe one could suggest to write a good wsgi script which could handle this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;htaccess&quot;&gt;.htaccess&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yet another way would be to make the .htaccess file dynamic, if it is possible. I don&amp;rsquo;t have any idea if I could write an apache config file that would trigger the correct wsgi file (which triggers the correct settings one). Maybe one could suggest a way of doing this (through regex?). To me thiss seems the best way which would trigger a corresponding process for each domain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;django-multisite&quot;&gt;django-multisite&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a django application I found (Source: https://github.com/shestera/django-multisite) which utilize &lt;strong&gt;thread locals&lt;/strong&gt; to dynamically define the SITE_ID setting according to the request domain. I have tried this and is actually working but as the django documentation has &lt;a href=&quot;http://code.djangoproject.com/wiki/CookBookThreadlocalsAndUser&quot;&gt;pretty clearly&lt;/a&gt; warned against its use, I am in doubt if it is a safe way. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Till now I am still unclear of what method to implement among the above or some other one. There are some pros and cons of all the methods.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I apologise if I have written something wrong, these all are only some methods I have found out while searching the web and discussing on the groups, so please specify if there is any mistake or you can suggest something related to this.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </entry>
    
    <entry>
        <title>Whiteboarding with XMPP (Google Talk)</title>
        <link href="http://www.rohanjain.in/hacking/2010/10/25/whiteboarding-with-xmpp-google-talk"/>
        <updated>2010-10-25T00:00:00+05:30</updated>
        <id>http://www.rohanjain.in/hacking/2010/10/25/whiteboarding-with-xmpp-google-talk</id>
        
        <category term="hacking" />
        
        <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Sometimes, being too lazy to use the type, you might wish for some other way to interact with others. Well there is one and quit an interactive and entertaining one, a whiteboarding interface, i.e. the people involved in chat can do collaborative drawings, play games, convey emotions not possible by typing etc. It can have some bigger implementations like teaching, presentations many more utilities can be innovated.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is already a small implementation of this feature in yahoo by name doodle. Seeing its utility one might wonder why this brilliant feature is not implemented with the widely used chat protocol, XMPP (Google Talk is based on XMPP)? Well I cant find out why not.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, we have taken an initiative. Our group (&lt;a href=&quot;http://github.com/crodjer&quot; title=&quot;&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Me&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://github.com/snktagarwal&quot; title=&quot;&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Sanket Agarwal&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://github.com/psjinx&quot; title=&quot;&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Pankaj Singh&lt;/a&gt;) is working for implementing this feature with the XMPP protocol, at least for pidgin users.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;technical-info&quot;&gt;Technical Info:&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Project Repository: &lt;a href=&quot;http://github.com/crodjer/pidgin_whiteboard&quot;&gt;http://github.com/crodjer/pidgin_whiteboard&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Updates: &lt;a href=&quot;#updates&quot;&gt;Project updates&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This project involves building a basic implementation of the protocol specified in,  &lt;a href=&quot;http://xmpp.org/extensions/xep-0284.html&quot;&gt;http://xmpp.org/extensions/xep-0284.html&lt;/a&gt;, using the SVG graphics specified in, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.w3.org/2000/svg&quot;&gt;http://www.w3.org/2000/svg&lt;/a&gt;. Both together define the standards for our work.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We hope to provide the following features:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Simple whiteboarding drawing Lines, Polygons, Circles and Free Curves.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fancy Texting&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Image Sending&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;This will provide users with a more enriching experience.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am really excited about this project as it would be one of my initial contributions to the great open-source community. Till now it have been a fine ride of purpling, jingling and jabbering with pidgin.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;updates&quot;&gt;Updates:&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;29 Nov 2010&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Work resumed after a brief pause. The target now is to integrate &lt;a href=&quot;http://xmpp.org/extensions/xep-0284.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;shared XML editing&lt;/a&gt; with jingle and add more features to the whiteboard graphical gui.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;10 Nov 2010&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Our Proof of concept is ready. All the basic features of whiteboard are now incorporated. A usable implementation now exists. You may fetch and compile the code from the git repository (Address mentioned above). This is how it looks:&lt;br /&gt;
&amp;lt;iframe width=&quot;425&quot; height=&quot;349&quot; src=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/embed/sYKutp4I4Zs&quot;&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/iframe&amp;gt;
A &lt;a href=&quot;http://img577.imageshack.us/img577/7910/screenshot1kg.png&quot;&gt;Snapshot&lt;/a&gt;.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;9 Nov 2010&lt;/em&gt;
Syncing of whiteboards is up. The whiteboards are updated as the two users draw using their brushes. So a responsive interface is present. Just some small bug fix and feature additions remain now.  &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://img259.imageshack.us/img259/7980/screenshotrd.png&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Screenshot&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;6 Nov 2010&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Now session initiate and accept integrated (popping up of whiteboard on both ends). Slight change in way of implementation, use of libjingle is now on a hold, creating a custom whiteboard message format for session management for now. Code in &lt;strong&gt;dcrodjer&lt;/strong&gt; branch of the above git repository. 
A screenshot of the code working: &lt;a href=&quot;http://img837.imageshack.us/img837/8250/screenshot1gb.png&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Image for session implementation&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;24 Oct 2010&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
A whiteboard interface initiates. This is how it look like:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://img841.imageshack.us/img841/5516/59586846.png&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Image 1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://img221.imageshack.us/img221/4198/65357038.png&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Image 2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </entry>
    

</feed>
