<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Blog on The Perpetual Amature</title>
    <link>/blog/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Blog on The Perpetual Amature</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-US</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 27 Feb 2017 06:15:12 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/blog/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>The two windows workflow</title>
      <link>/the-two-windows-workflow/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Feb 2017 06:15:12 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/the-two-windows-workflow/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I was introduced to OSX for the first time in September, 2015. Coming from a
XMonad/Linux based setup, I was accustomed to powerful and fast window
management. Any OSX based solution for window management system I tried, lacked
these qualities. I tried:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Amethyst&lt;/em&gt;, window manager with basic XMonad bindings.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Just type the application name in &lt;em&gt;Alfred&lt;/em&gt;. Initially this was slow, but
quickly became habitual.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mjolinr&lt;/em&gt;, which is configured in Lua and can actually be quite powerful.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Numerous other programs out there which try to solve the same problem in
similar fashion.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These programs sort of worked, but they are appallingly slow and unresponsive.
OSX is full of unnecessary animations and bloat which makes everything feel
laggy and slow. Alfred based switching works on application level and not window
level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eventually, I noticed that &lt;code&gt;Cmd-Tab&lt;/code&gt; based window switching is fast. So, for
last 6 months, I have been using a two window strategy. That is:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The primary workflow must be dependent on only two windows.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This means that any application I want to have in my workflow must run in either
of those windows.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those windows in my case are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;iTerm2&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
This includes a &lt;code&gt;tmux&lt;/code&gt; session, with multiple windows. The first window will
run a in-terminal emacs client and the rest all windows will various shell
sessions and split configurations of their own. This way, I&amp;rsquo;ll spend most of
my time within a tmux session.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Browser&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Apart from functioning as a browser, it serves as an host for applications
such as: Mail, Slack, Calender.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are multiple benefits of this setup:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Quick window switching. Way faster than any solutions out there.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This flow is much more universal and works on most systems: RaspberryPi,
remote machines, Linux TTY.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Keystrokes are deterministic. When computer gets unresponsive, you don&amp;rsquo;t want
to be blocked. Just queue in the keystrokes and let the computer execute
things at its own pace. This also is my major complaint against touch phones
(compared to say, an old Nokia QWERTY phone).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I use Vim as a text editor for anything non Clojure. With this, I can have a
vertical split (Vim on left and multiple accompanying terminals on right).
This is a further reduction in context switch.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are drawbacks too:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Not every application can run in the browser/terminal. Because of this, you
end up negotiating for alternates.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Although most of Emacs works well in terminal, some bindings at times won&amp;rsquo;t
work. This isn&amp;rsquo;t a issue for me particularly.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This doesn&amp;rsquo;t solve all of the OSX related annoyances.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Decentralized Twitter</title>
      <link>/decentralized-twitter/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 11 Feb 2017 15:20:45 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/decentralized-twitter/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;As a social network, twitter has a few fairly unique characteristics:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It forces people to be more creative in trying to express the idea within 140
characters.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ability to control the content that you receive. Stricter filtering is
possible based on one&amp;rsquo;s interests.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;On platforms such as Quora/Facebook, the feed is not deterministic. That&amp;rsquo;s
not the case with twitter. You see tweets in order and as they happen.
Twitter doesn&amp;rsquo;t try to decide what is important and what is not.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But Twitter has been bleeding money since I have known about it. It has
seemingly created a lot of value in sharing of ideas and news. If it were to go
away, it&amp;rsquo;ll have an (at least temporary) impact on its users.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Are there any alternatives to Twitter? Sometime back, I started a casual
discussion about this with a friend. There isn&amp;rsquo;t an obvious service that
currently exists which would fill in the void that Twitter might leave. Other
than what Twitter what already provides, we needed something more resilient. So,
it could be de-centralized, i.e. not dependent on a single server to provide
content.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hmm, we want a client-server architecture. It could be a standardized protocol.
Services would spin up for non-tech people so that they could host their content
on them. Then because of the standardized protocol, people could innovate on
clients as well! Continue the discussion on this for a few more seconds and
then&amp;hellip;wait! This already exists. The world already uses it, and quiet
successfully. And, it is an open standard. We were trying to invent blogs and
RSS!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And there was an end to a short brainstorming session.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Navigating with the first telescope</title>
      <link>/telescope/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 May 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/telescope/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;In my &lt;a href=&#34;/sky/&#34;&gt;previous post&lt;/a&gt;, I wrote about my initial experiences with stargazing -
primarily to demonstrate that it can be fascinating without fancy
equipment. After those initial sessions, I bought a telescope which magnified my
experience significantly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stars. Stars everywhere!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-telescope&#34;&gt;The Telescope&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The primary purpose of an (astronomical) telescope, unlike popular belief, is
not actually magnification. They act as light collectors (think burning a paper
with a converging lens and sunlight).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because the aperture of our eye is very small (7mm at best), we don&amp;rsquo;t capture
enough light to see faint stars. Telescopes (and binoculars) can have much
larger objectives and hence more surface area where the photon can hit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Buying a telescope (or anything?) on an impulse is a bad idea. There are
multiple articles/guides (like &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.skyandtelescope.com/astronomy-equipment/how-to-choose-a-telescope/&#34;&gt;this one&lt;/a&gt;) that talk about various
telescopes and their purposes. I&amp;rsquo;d recommend going through a few of those while
having some direct gazing sessions, helps in setting up the preferences and
expectations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I personally enjoy looking at faint stars and deep sky objects or DSOs (star
clusters, galaxies, nebulae) more compared to planets/moon. To start with, the
objects that Charles Messier &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_Messier_objects&#34;&gt;catalogued&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My telescope is a Newtonian reflector with a &lt;strong&gt;114mm&lt;/strong&gt; aperture and &lt;strong&gt;900mm&lt;/strong&gt;
focal length. I have 3 kellner eyepieces of sizes (and magnifications) &lt;strong&gt;25mm
(36x)&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;10mm (90x)&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;4mm (225x)&lt;/strong&gt;. It has a &lt;strong&gt;6x24&lt;/strong&gt; (i.e. 6x
magnification and 24mm aperture) finder. To keep the weight (and price) at a
minimum, I got an Altazimuth mount.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the web, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B0000Y8C2Y/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;camp=1789&amp;amp;creative=9325&amp;amp;creativeASIN=B0000Y8C2Y&amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;tag=crodjer-20&amp;amp;linkId=H3RLG5OMNQX6ZMOH&#34;&gt;this scope&lt;/a&gt; is similar to mine. But I&amp;rsquo;d actually
recommend &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B001DDW9UW/ref=as_li_qf_sp_asin_il_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;camp=1789&amp;amp;creative=9325&amp;amp;creativeASIN=B001DDW9UW&amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;tag=crodjer-20&amp;amp;linkId=U6A22R7IFLTDIBPQ.amazon.com/gp/product/B001DDW9UW&#34;&gt;Orion XT6&lt;/a&gt; for much better observations or &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B00D12U1IK/ref=as_li_qf_sp_asin_il_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;camp=1789&amp;amp;creative=9325&amp;amp;creativeASIN=B00D12U1IK&amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;tag=crodjer-20&amp;amp;linkId=XUNVRD64WYTFUT6U&#34;&gt;Orion StarBlast 4.5&lt;/a&gt;
for its portability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;finding-things&#34;&gt;Finding things&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Star_hopping#The_technique&#34;&gt;Star hopping&lt;/a&gt; is the technique that is conventionally used by armature
astronomers. But with star charts, I also have &lt;a href=&#34;http://stellarium.org/&#34;&gt;Stellarium&lt;/a&gt;, with which I get
precise details of much fainter stars. Once having pointed the scope to a bright
star, I synchronize my path with Stellarium. Because I am comparing stars in sky
to a star in telescope, it is possible for me to end up at the exact locations
of a DSO even if I can&amp;rsquo;t discern it because of light pollution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ll write more about this in a future post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;orion-nebula-m42&#34;&gt;Orion Nebula (M42)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Orion_Nebula&#34;&gt;Orion Nebula&lt;/a&gt; is the brightest diffuse nebula in the sky and lies in the
constellation Orion (which also hosts my favorite star, Betelgeuse). Although it
looks nothing like the colourful and detailed photos on the internet. I see it
as a fuzzy extended grey object, similar to
&lt;a href=&#34;http://messier.seds.org/Pics/History/m42m.jpg&#34;&gt;Charles Messier&amp;rsquo;s sketch&lt;/a&gt;. It is remarkable, nevertheless. The four
young stars in its heart are distinctly noticeable. When Orion was accessible,
it was a ritual for me spend a few minutes on it before anything else.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Orion Nebula is an example of a stellar nursery where new stars are being
born.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;open-star-clusters&#34;&gt;Open star clusters&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of all the DSOs, I find open star clusters the most exciting. I like to examine
their finer details, matching each star with Stellarium&amp;rsquo;s rendering.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The constellation &lt;strong&gt;Canis Major&lt;/strong&gt; hosts a few prominent clusters. &lt;strong&gt;M41&lt;/strong&gt; was
the first cluster I ever saw. It is fairly bright. I even sketched the star
pattern on paper, which now stays on my table at work. &lt;strong&gt;NGC 2362 (Canis Major
cluster)&lt;/strong&gt;, although not actually from the Messier catalogue, is also
interesting. Most of its brightness comes from the star τ Canis Majoris. I
noticed it when I was meandering around the lower part of the constellation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I saw a few clusters in and around the &lt;strong&gt;Puppis&lt;/strong&gt; constellation. &lt;strong&gt;M93&lt;/strong&gt; is a
nice and bright cluster. At the time of my observation, M93 was straight above
the star &lt;strong&gt;Asmidiske (ξ Pup)&lt;/strong&gt;. Asmidiske, being yellow, is a sight in
itself. It has two companion stars nearby. &lt;strong&gt;M47&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;M46&lt;/strong&gt; are categorized
to be in Puppis, but I used Canis Major, Hydra and Monoceros as reference for
them. M47 is bright, but M46 isn&amp;rsquo;t as noticeable with my setup.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Taurus&lt;/strong&gt; had a significance for me as the host to &lt;strong&gt;Pleiades (M45)&lt;/strong&gt;. It is a
cluster of very bright stars, with the brightest few visible without any optical
instruments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;M35&lt;/strong&gt; in &lt;strong&gt;Gemini&lt;/strong&gt; is yet another bright cluster that I observed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;planets&#34;&gt;Planets&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Planets are like stars but brighter and without the twinkling. With a telescope,
a few more details may be seen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The planet I have most observed is &lt;strong&gt;Jupiter&lt;/strong&gt;. Initially, to my disappointment,
I could only make out an extend bright white disk. Eventually, my skills
improved (Jupiter moved toward opposition as well) and I could actually make out
the colors and the stripes. By coincidence I even got to see the great red
spot. Jupiter rotates about its axis very fast (8 hour days), and I never had
actually planned a sighting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By Jupiter&amp;rsquo;s moving toward opposition, its the Earth&amp;rsquo;s movement in between the
Sun and Jupiter which has significance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of all the planets, I was most interested in &lt;strong&gt;Saturn&lt;/strong&gt;. Having straightened my
expectations, I was not disappointed on first sight. The ring is indeed present
and looks beautiful. I haven&amp;rsquo;t been able to see the Cassini&amp;rsquo;s division yet
though. More sitting of Saturn gazing are upcoming.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mars&lt;/strong&gt; is a red/orange disk with no other features visible (yet). I saw
&lt;strong&gt;Venus&lt;/strong&gt; only for a few minutes. Its unlikely that I&amp;rsquo;d be able to see
&lt;strong&gt;Mercury&lt;/strong&gt; from where I am.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Moon&lt;/strong&gt; (although not a planet) can be seen in fine details. It is the only
object which is bright enough to take photos of with my phone&amp;rsquo;s camera. But
other than that, I find it uninteresting. Moreover, it obliterates my eye&amp;rsquo;s dark
adjustment. Moonless nights are the best for stargazing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;nebulae-globular-clusters-and-galaxies&#34;&gt;Nebulae, Globular clusters and Galaxies&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These tend to be faint and the city lights takes away the required contrast for
their visibility. My eyes probably caught photons originating from even the ones
I couldn&amp;rsquo;t identify, because I verify the location I am pointing at based on the
nearby faint stars.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The DSO which took up most of my time is &lt;strong&gt;M1 (Crab nebula)&lt;/strong&gt;. It is a supernova
remnant in &lt;strong&gt;Taurus&lt;/strong&gt;. I must have put in 6+ hours cumulative in attempts to
observe it. Infact, I remember much of the star patterns near the nebula. But,
wouldn&amp;rsquo;t claim to have seen the nebula itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another such object is &lt;strong&gt;M78&lt;/strong&gt;, a reflection nebula in &lt;strong&gt;Orion&lt;/strong&gt;. I have the
nearby star patterns for it memorized as well. If at all, I saw a very dark grey
and fuzzy object. &lt;strong&gt;M43&lt;/strong&gt; is nebula right beside Orion nebula. I couldn&amp;rsquo;t
discern it at all though, because of the imposing adjacent nebula.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;M53&lt;/strong&gt;, a globular cluster in Coma Berenices, is visible as a dim round grey
object. &lt;strong&gt;M68&lt;/strong&gt; is a globular cluster in Hydra. But I could not clearly
distinguish it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;M104&lt;/strong&gt; (Sombrero Galaxy) lies near Virgo. I recently started observing it. I
did notice the presence of something, but may just be an illusion. The view
should improve in the future sightings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;limiting-magnitude&#34;&gt;Limiting Magnitude&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In astronomy, &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Limiting_magnitude&#34;&gt;limiting magnitude&lt;/a&gt; is the faintest apparent magnitude of a
celestial body that is detectable or detected by a given instrument.&lt;br /&gt;
- Wikipedia&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I find figuring out the limiting magnitude for my telescope interesting.
Theoretically, I should be able to see stars up to an apparent magnitude of
&lt;strong&gt;12.8&lt;/strong&gt;, but I can&amp;rsquo;t actually. The lower the apparent magnitude of on object,
the brighter it is. My skills, light pollution, quality of optics and the
atmosphere bring this down significantly. The faintest stars I have seen, with
significant effort, are roughly of magnitude &lt;strong&gt;11.2&lt;/strong&gt;. Usually, I can
conveniently see stars upto &lt;strong&gt;10&lt;/strong&gt; and with a bit of effort (a second or so of
concentration), &lt;strong&gt;10.5&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because of how our eye are designed, moving it during observations and using
&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Averted_vision&#34;&gt;averted vision&lt;/a&gt; improves the ability to distinguish very low contrast
objects.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Gazing in the night sky</title>
      <link>/sky/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 May 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/sky/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;About 6 months ago, I picked up a new hobby: Stargazing. Starting off with just
naked eyes, I quickly realized that there is actually quite a lot to see without
any optical equipment. &lt;a href=&#34;https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.google.android.stardroid&amp;amp;hl=en&#34;&gt;Sky Map&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://stellarium.org/&#34;&gt;Stellarium&lt;/a&gt; are incredibly useful
applications for a dilettante like me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;dark-adjustment&#34;&gt;Dark adjustment&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before any stargazing session, dark adjustment i.e. dilating the pupils
completely to improve night vision, is essential. I turn off all kinds of lights
in the house and listen to podcasts for a while (at least 30 minutes).  I go out
to stargaze when the outside looks brighter than inside.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Avoiding the bright lights from neighbours can be a challenge though. Moon&amp;rsquo;s an
issue as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;constellations&#34;&gt;Constellations&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Apparent_magnitude&#34;&gt;apparent magnitude&lt;/a&gt; (m) of a celestial object is a number that is a
measure of its brightness as seen by an observer on Earth. The smaller the
number, the
brighter a star appears.&lt;br /&gt;
- Wikipedia&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the time I started, the most identifiable constellation was
&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Orion_(constellation)&#34;&gt;Orion&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Betelgeuse&#34;&gt;Betelgeuse&lt;/a&gt;, reddish orange star in Orion, very quickly became my
favorite star. It gets the designation α Orionis even though Rigel is the
brightest star in Orion (β Orionis). Betelgeuse&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Apparent_magnitude&#34;&gt;apparent magnitude&lt;/a&gt; varies
between 0-1.3, making it at times the brightest star in Orion. The star is
huge - 630 times the radius of the sun. It was the first star (other than the
Sun) to be imaged beyond a point source.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Taurus_(constellation)&#34;&gt;Taurus&lt;/a&gt; is another constellation that I observed in my initial stargazing
period. It extends over a large area, so not as identifiable. But it is a host
for a unique star cluster: &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pleiades&#34;&gt;Pleiades&lt;/a&gt;. The 5-6 bright stars in the cluster are
a singular sight with naked eyes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Canis_Major&#34;&gt;Canis Major&lt;/a&gt; also has a significance for me as the host for &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sirius&#34;&gt;Sirius&lt;/a&gt; (the
brightest star). Its relatively close, being only about 8.6 light years away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There were some other constellations as well, but I haven&amp;rsquo;t paid them too much
attention. Listing some off the top of my head: Gemini, Puppis, Hydra and
Virgo. But I couldn&amp;rsquo;t identify them without Orion / Canis Major as anchors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;moon&#34;&gt;Moon&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moon&amp;rsquo;s the most noticeable and obvious site in the sky. At times, based on the
shape of the moon&amp;rsquo;s bright portion, I&amp;rsquo;d try to visualize how the Sun, the Moon
and the Earth are positioned relative to each other. The &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/22°_halo&#34;&gt;22° halo&lt;/a&gt; around
the moon is also nice to look at. To be honest though, I am always more
interested in the Moon&amp;rsquo;s absence, since it impacts the visibility of stars
significantly. It also damages my eye&amp;rsquo;s dark adjustment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;planets&#34;&gt;Planets&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first 6 planets are readily visible to the naked eye. Although, Earth&amp;rsquo;s
little too close to have an astronomical perspective. Because planets are at a
distance and visible as extend objects, they don&amp;rsquo;t twinkle. This makes it easy
to differentiate them from stars. Even &lt;a href=&#34;http://apod.nasa.gov/apod/ap000725.html&#34;&gt;Betelgeuse&lt;/a&gt;
twinkles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;March this year, Jupiter was at the opposition (Earth being roughly in between
the Sun and Jupiter) and had its closest approach to us. Hence, it was at its
brightest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Venus is always very bright (3rd brightest after the Sun and the Moon), but is
visible near the Sunrise and the Sunset (hence called the morning/evening star).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mars and Saturn as of now are located nearby. Mars is bright reddish in color
and Saturn is yellowish in color.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;22nd January 2016 was a interesting day for planet watching. The 5 planets were
&lt;a href=&#34;http://news.nationalgeographic.com/2015/12/160120-planet-parade-stargazing-astronomy/&#34;&gt;all aligned&lt;/a&gt; for the first time in over a decade.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The path that the Sun and the planets take also point toward the flatness of the
solar system. Feels nice to get some empirical evidence of this, against just
having this told.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;artificial-objects&#34;&gt;Artificial objects&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few artificial objects orbiting the Earth can be seen as well. For them, the
sunset happens later (or sunrise earlier) than us, providing us with the dark
background and enough contrast for the sunlight they reflect. The International
Space Station (ISS), because of its size ends up being brighter than even
Venus. &lt;a href=&#34;https://spotthestation.nasa.gov/&#34;&gt;This NASA&amp;rsquo;s site&lt;/a&gt; can be used to plan an ISS sighting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Satellite_flare#Iridium_flares&#34;&gt;Iridium&lt;/a&gt; satellites&amp;rsquo; flares are also noticeable at times. There are ways to
plan their sightings, but I haven&amp;rsquo;t done that yet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;limiting-magnitude-lm&#34;&gt;Limiting Magnitude (LM)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In astronomy, &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Limiting_magnitude&#34;&gt;limiting magnitude&lt;/a&gt; is the faintest apparent magnitude of a
celestial body that is detectable or detected by a given instrument.&lt;br /&gt;
- Wikipedia&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like to calculate the limiting magnitude. This would give me an idea of the
light pollution and what I should expect to see. I notice light pollution in
Pune is (unsurprisingly) more than that in Jaipur. From
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.imo.net/visual/major/observation/lm&#34;&gt;these charts&lt;/a&gt;, I calculated the LM at Pune to be about 4.5. I came
to doubt that when I eventually started using &lt;a href=&#34;http://stellarium.org/&#34;&gt;Stellarium&lt;/a&gt;. The naked eye LM
at my place is roughly 3.5 - 3.8.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I should give using the charts another try. At the time, I had used the Tau
(using stars in/near Taurus) chart which has a magnitude gap of 1.62 between 3
and 4 visible stars.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;wonders&#34;&gt;Wonders&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stargazing results in multiple interesting and unsettling thoughts:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When I see a star, the photons hitting my eyes are 1000s of year old. For
example: Light from Betelgeuse travels for roughly 643 years to reach us.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I are literally looking at the past of those stars. But again, at these
scales, the concept of present can be doubted. Einstein talks about the &lt;em&gt;The
relativity of simultaneity&lt;/em&gt; in &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/1420946331/ref=as_li_qf_sp_asin_il_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;camp=1789&amp;amp;creative=9325&amp;amp;creativeASIN=1420946331&amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;tag=crodjer-20&amp;amp;linkId=CY4F7W7SQWMXRNIL&#34;&gt;his book&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The insignificance of the Earth&amp;rsquo;s and us with it in the universe.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We most probably aren&amp;rsquo;t alone.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How amazingly useful constellations are in navigating the sky.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How made up constellations are and the irrational significance humans give to
them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;telescope&#34;&gt;Telescope&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a month of naked eye stargazing, I bought a telescope (similar to
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B0000Y8C2Y/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;camp=1789&amp;amp;creative=9325&amp;amp;creativeASIN=B0000Y8C2Y&amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;tag=crodjer-20&amp;amp;linkId=H3RLG5OMNQX6ZMOH&#34;&gt;this one&lt;/a&gt; but with better eyepieces) from a local
provider. I&amp;rsquo;ll write about my observations with that over the next few days.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Edit&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The post on my experience with a telescope has now been published
&lt;a href=&#34;/telescope/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>You have infinite email addresses</title>
      <link>/infi-mail/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 02 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/infi-mail/</guid>
      <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;tl;dr&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
You can add arbitrary tags to your email address. Any email sent to
&lt;code&gt;your-email+tag@your-provider.ext&lt;/code&gt; will land in the inbox for
&lt;code&gt;your-email@your-provider.ext&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Emails are important. They are your identity on the web. Just like on phone,
you&amp;rsquo;d want to control who can contact you via email. This warrants caution in
signing up at places on the internet. It can be unsafe to register with the
personal email address on new services for multiple reasons:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bulk data breaches &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.huffingtonpost.com/entry/biggest-worst-data-breaches-hacks_us_55d4b5a5e4b07addcb44fd9e&#34;&gt;are fairly common&lt;/a&gt;. You don&amp;rsquo;t want your
email address out there for bots around the world to feed on.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The service you are signing up for may itself be malicious. Or worse, it may
be Facebook!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Same email address on every service can make it simpler for bots to break
into your accounts once they succeed in attacking one.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.fullcontact.com/gmail/&#34;&gt;are actual services&lt;/a&gt; dedicated for creating single
points of catastrophic failures utilizing email addresses.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These sound upsetting, but are indeed manageable to an extent. One trick that I
use is &lt;em&gt;tagging the email address&lt;/em&gt;. It is a fairly common practice among
programmers. Most popular email services support this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What do I mean by tagging? Lets take Jon&amp;rsquo;s email: &lt;code&gt;jon.snow@email.wf&lt;/code&gt;. His
sister, Arya, will know this address as is. But for the untrustworthy
Lannisters, he tags the email: &lt;code&gt;jon.snow+lannister@email.wf&lt;/code&gt;. When someone
writes to this address: he will receive the mails knowing that Lannisters were
involved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;email.wf&lt;/code&gt; here is a fictional service, analogous to &lt;code&gt;gmail.com&lt;/code&gt;. I didn&amp;rsquo;t
want to accidentally use an actual email address.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One may use a similar technique while signing up for services on the
internet. Say Jon wants to register on &lt;code&gt;nightswatch.got&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In &lt;em&gt;Night&amp;rsquo;s Watch&lt;/em&gt; registration form, he&amp;rsquo;d use
&lt;code&gt;jon.snow+nighstwatch@email.wf&lt;/code&gt; as the email. The tag &lt;code&gt;+nighstwatch&lt;/code&gt; here is
arbitrarily chosen.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Jon will get the confirmation mail in the original account. Being prudent,
he&amp;rsquo;ll verify that the mail it does have the correct tag in the &lt;em&gt;to address&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Also, &lt;code&gt;email.wf&lt;/code&gt; lets Jon send emails with the tagged address. This is useful
for talking to the customer care. GMail users can go to:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;code&gt;Settings -&amp;gt; Accounts and Import -&amp;gt; Add another email address you own&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;br /&gt;
and filling up the form with the tagged address.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This means Jon can have practically infinite email addresses. Why is this
helpful?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Jon can collect all the mails from &lt;em&gt;Night&amp;rsquo;s Watch&lt;/em&gt; at one place, specially
when their mails aren&amp;rsquo;t consistent enough to write filters.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If the credentials for the &lt;em&gt;Night&amp;rsquo;s Watch&lt;/em&gt; account were to be leaked, say
through Phishing, other more important services like the email account itself
would not be as vulnerable.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;One cannot track Jon&amp;rsquo;s movements across various accounts/profiles through his
email.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sites which don&amp;rsquo;t allow tags in the email address can be a red flags for
Jon. He can assume that they&amp;rsquo;d have terrible developers/management and look
for alternates.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Making this into a habit will require a bit of discipline. But eventually, it
gets instinctive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On a related note, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/1118958470/ref=as_li_qf_sp_asin_il_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;camp=1789&amp;amp;creative=9325&amp;amp;creativeASIN=1118958470&amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;tag=crodjer-20&amp;amp;linkId=244BG6VSA5AT2K5S&#34;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; is an interesting book, that talks
about Phishing through email in the real world.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Switch between networks based on availability</title>
      <link>/route-to/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Aug 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/route-to/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Having been blessed with an unreliable internet, I always have had the need to
change the default route when one goes down. &lt;a href=&#34;http://linux.die.net/man/8/ip&#34;&gt;ip&lt;/a&gt; provides you the required
tooling to do that. I had been doing it so often, that I ended up writing a
function to do this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-bash&#34;&gt;route_to () {
    interface=$1
    route=$(ip route | grep $interface | sed -r &#39;s/\.0\/[[:digit:]]{2,3} /.1 /&#39; | cut -d &#39; &#39; -f -4)
    if [ -n &amp;quot;$route&amp;quot; ]; then
        sudo ip route del default &amp;amp;&amp;gt; /dev/null
        sudo ip route replace default via $route
    else
        echo &amp;quot;No routes match: $interface&amp;quot; &amp;gt;&amp;amp;2
    fi
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With this in available in my shell, I can simply do &lt;code&gt;route_to wlan0&lt;/code&gt; and my
system will start using &lt;code&gt;wlan0&lt;/code&gt; as the default interface.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>VNC over reverse SSH</title>
      <link>/vnc/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 10 May 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/vnc/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;About a year ago, I switched my parents computer (lets call it &lt;code&gt;P&lt;/code&gt;) from the
pre-installed OS (Windows) to Ubuntu. The primary reason for this switch was it
hard for me to debug and fix issues. Things have been smooth after the switch
with no issues which I found hard to fix remotely. What specially has worked is
my ability to log in to the computer when its on through my VPS and service it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;reverse-ssh&#34;&gt;Reverse SSH&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whenever &lt;code&gt;P&lt;/code&gt; starts, it makes a reverse SSH connection to my VPS. I use
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.archlinux.org/packages/community/x86_64/autossh/&#34;&gt;autossh&lt;/a&gt; to monitor and make sure that it is eventually always
connected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-bash&#34;&gt;$ autossh -M 10001 -f -NXYR 10000:localhost:22 vps
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here &lt;code&gt;vps&lt;/code&gt; is a SSH alias for my personal VPS.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can tunnel through the VPS and login to &lt;code&gt;P&lt;/code&gt; via VPS using the following SSH
configuration:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-config&#34;&gt;Host home
     Hostname localhost
     User username
     Port 10000
     ProxyCommand ssh -e none -W %h:%p vps
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To log in to &lt;code&gt;P&lt;/code&gt; transparently, I can simply do:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-bash&#34;&gt;$ ssh home
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I use this to resolve most of the issues. Of course it does have the requirement
that the system be booted up and connected to a network.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;vnc&#34;&gt;VNC&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There also can be issues which have to do with the GUI (say browser maintenance)
and cannot be done easily over a text SSH session. For those cases, VNC is to
rescue. I create a VNC server on &lt;code&gt;P&lt;/code&gt; using &lt;a href=&#34;https://wiki.archlinux.org/index.php/X11vnc&#34;&gt;x11vnc&lt;/a&gt; and tunnel the VNC
port to my local through SSH. Now, I can access &lt;code&gt;P&lt;/code&gt;&amp;rsquo;s graphical session remotely
via a vnc client (mine is &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.archlinux.org/packages/community/x86_64/tigervnc/&#34;&gt;tigervnc&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-bash&#34;&gt;$ ssh home -L 5900:localhost:5900 &amp;quot;x11vnc -rfbauth ~/.vnc/passwd -display :0 -noxdamage&amp;quot;
$ vncviewer localhost::5900 -QualityLevel 3 -CompressLevel 6
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This method is much better compared to the more common solutions such has
Google&amp;rsquo;s VNC chrome extension or other proprietary services. But they are slow
and untrustable 3rd parties. With this way of setting up VNC, everything is
protected under SSH connections.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>